Guide to the Watson Nicholson Papers, ca. 1903-1921
Department of Special Collections
Watson Nicholson Papers,
ca. 1903-1921
Special Collections M0157
Nicholson, Watson, 1866-1951.
4 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Provenance
Gift of W. Nicholson, ca. 1950.
Scope and Content
Literary manuscripts, research notes, copies of research material, clips, lectures, essays, printed material. Predominantly research material and manuscripts of published works on British theatre. Some unpublished material. Other subjects include; censorship, Victorian era, Thackeray, Defoe's JOURNAL OF THE PLAGUE YEAR, and various English literature topics.
Biographical Note
1866, Sept. 23 born, Pendleton, Ind., son of Abraham and Maria (Davis) Nicholson. student through junior year at Indiana U.
1884 - 1887 teacher in Indiana schools
1892 A.B., Stanford
1892 - 1894, 1897 - 1901 teacher in California schools
1895 M.A., Harvard Graduate School
1895 - 1897 teacher at Harvard
1897, Sept. 1 married Florence Emily Beaver
1903 Ph.D., Yale
1903 - 1905 engaged in university extension teaching
1905 and 1907 traveled and studied in Europe
1905 - 1908 instructor, English Literature at Sheffield Scientific School (Yale)
1910 - 1915 worked in British Museum Member: Harvard Teachers' Association, A.A.A.S., American Academy of Political and Social Science, Phi Beta Kappa, Sigma Chi. Hon. Member: Mark Twain Society Clubs: Authors' (London); Stanford, Fortnightly, Harvard, Yale Author: A Syllabus of Six Lectures on American Literature with bibliography, 1903; The Struggle for a Free Stage in London, 1906; discovered all the sources of Defoe's famous Journal (1913), previously regarded as fiction, published as Historical Sources of Defoe's Journal of the Plague Year, 1919; Anthony Aston, Stroller and Adventurer, 1920.
1951, Dec. 2 died - last address: Michigan
Container List
- Patents, petitions, grants and other documents from the Patent Office and Lord Chamberlain's office and other archives in London, relating to the theaters, patentees, managers, actors, etc., transcriptions of Vol. I - Tudors and Stuarts. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Patents, etc. - Transcriptions of Vol. II, includes correspondence with and notes for Lucy Drucker, transcriber, 1920and 1921,holograph transcriptions and appendices - chron. list of important facts connected with history of theatrical monopoly, copies of various theatrical patents and licences, Parliamentary legislation regulating plays and players, copies of plans for proposed new theatres, copies of petitions and other docs. re: Council proceedings, of 1810for a third theater, copies of docs. illustrative of struggle between 1832and 1843,misc., alphabetical list of minor theaters established in London prior to 1843,bibliography. (Box 1, Volume 2 (vol.))
- Miscellaneous Notes - The Minor Theaters (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Reports of Select Committees 1832, 1853, 1866, 1892, 1909 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Miscellany - list of Lords Chamberlain and Examiners, bibliography of censored plays, laws regulating theater and drama in England, state of the London stage at various periods 1844 - 1873,censorship considered by critics, etc., censorship - examples of absurdities, Archer notes - Shaw's criticism - Cibber notes, censorship in France, 19th century stage in England, Strictures by Zangwill, Filin, Fortnightly Review, TLS 1921J.M. Stillman. (Box 2, Folder 5)
- 18th Century - Manners, Coronation of George II, Chapter from The Struggle - Little Theater & G.F., Goodman's Field Theater, Revolt of 1733, censored plays. (Box 2, Folder 6)
- 19th Century - Notes - Lenten controversy, censored plays, clippings, censorship in France. (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Censored Plays - newspaper clips. and some notes. ALS 1909Frank E. Bryant. (Box 3, Folder 8)
- The Struggle for a Free Stage in London -, 2 ptd., unbound, uncut copies. (Box 3, Folder 9)
- The Victorian Era - notes and misc. notes on Thackeray's works. Tennyson, Browning (Lounsbury); Vanity Fair, Pendennis, Yellowplush Correspondence, Christmas Books, Sketch Books, Esmond, Newcomes. (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Early Writings of W. Makepeace Thackeray, I and II. (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Early Writings of W. Makepeace Thackeray, II, III, IV and V. Notes by Watson Nicholson from contemporary sources. (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Thomas Betterton and His Colleagues, I. A Study of the Restoration and Post-Restoration Stage and Drama. Notes and copies of - Patent Rolls (1639 - 1664),Docs. from Ld. Chamberlain's Office (1660 - 1685). (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Thomas Betterton and His Colleagues, II. Short study on actors and managers., (typescript) (Box 4, Folder 14)
- The Restoration and Post-Restoration Drama, Thomas Betterton and his Colleagues, III - Sheridaniana., (notes) (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Historical Sources of Defoe's Journal of the Plague Year and Anthony Aston, Stroller and Adventurer original notes. ALS E. Carter, A.S. Salley, Jr. TLS Oscar Wegelin. (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Historical Sources of Defoe's Journal of the Plague Year (1919)and Anthony Aston, Stroller and Adventurer (1920)original mss. (Box 5, Folder 17)
- A Diary of the Plague Year., 2 bound copies of earlier version (bound together), typescript with corrections, some mss. (Box 5, Volume 18 (vol.))
- Essays - Literary and otherwise - by Watson Nicholson. Use of the Iliad and Odyssey in Lit. Classes. Aims and methods, aims and scope of English Lit. in Secondary Schools, Science and Rhetoric, Analysis of Structure of Silas Marner, Critical discussion of Bulwer's Pelham, Christopher Marlowe, Dryden's Prefaces, Massachusetts New (currency) Emission: An Episode in American Colonial Finance, Russian Diplomacy as a Factor in the Downfall of Napolean, Russian Diplomacy vs. Napoleonism in War of 1812. (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - includes reprints, typescripts (some with ms. corrections).
- Nicholsoniana - Unpublished mss. by Watson Nicholson. Who was Thackeray before Vanity Fair?, Early Writings of Wm. Makepeace Thackeray, Contemporary Estimate of William Makepeace Thackeray, Debit and Credit Account of Jack Wilton, Side Glances at Dramatic Censorship in England, True History of A Grunenwald Romance, or the Confessions of a Neb (short story), Wm. Lyon Phelps, An Appreciation. (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - typescript with ms. corrections, one holograph ms.
- Evolution of the Master of the Revels - Notes I Notes on the Revels, Revels to 1610., - ms. notes, clips. (Box 6, Folder 21)
- II, (Commonwealth, etc.). (Box 6, Folder 22)
- III, Restoration. (Box 7, Folder 23)
- IV, 1611 - 1640. (Box 7, Folder 24)
- V, Sir Henry Herbert regime. - Evolution of the Master of the Revels - Mss., original mss., unpublished, imcomplete. 1st of a planned three vol. History of the Censorship of the English Stage. (Box 7, Folder 25)
- Chapters I and II, two versions, typescript with ms. corrections. (Box 7, Folder 26)
- Chapters III - VI, typescript with ms. corrections. (Box 7, Folder 27)
- Chapters VII and VIII, manuscript - holograph. Chapter X, holograph notes (no Chapter IX)., typescript with ms. corrections (Box 7, Folder 28 - 29)
  - TLS [F.R. Lounsbury?].
- Lincoln Notes and Lecture (Box 8, Folder 30)
- Notes for Lectures on English Lit (Yale 1901 - 1908).The 17th century, Poets, Elizabethan Prose Writers. (Box 8, Folder 31)
- Miscellaneous Printed Material and Photo - theater programs, syllabus, articles., (2) (Box 8, Folder 32)
- Periander, Tyrant of Corinth - bound, unpublished play by Mrs. Nicholson. (Box 8, Folder 33)